
================================================================================
File: Vinogradova and Yakubov 2003 - Dynamic Effects on Force Measurements. 2. Lubrication and the Atomic Force Microscope.pdf
================================================================================
Number of pages: 8
Dynamic Effects on Force Measurements. 2. Lubrication
and the Atomic Force Microscope
Olga I. Vinogradova*,窶,窶｡and Gleb E. Yakubov窶,窶｡
Max Planck Institute for Polymer Research, Postfach 3148, D-55021 Mainz, Germany, and
Laboratory of Physical Chemistry of Modified Surfaces, Institute of Physical Chemistry,
Russian Academy of Sciences, 31 Leninsky Prospect, 117915 Moscow, Russia
Received August 16, 2002. In Final Form: December 2, 2002
We present the results of investigations of high-speed drainage of a thin film confined between a microscopic
colloidal probe and a substrate performed with a new atomic force microscope-related setup. Theoreticalcalculations are used to formulate the governing equation (force balance) for instantaneous deflection ofa cantilever spring, which is due to both concentrated forces acting on a colloidal probe and viscous dragforce on a cantilever itself. The suggested way to subtract the latter contribution allows design of a lubricationexperiment. Two pairs of interacting solids, characterized by different wettability and smoothness, immersedinto water -electrolyte solutions have been studied. Results for hydrophilic silica surfaces are in excellent
agreement with the Reynolds theory of hydrodynamic lubrication. Faster drainage of a thin film confinedbetween hydrophobic rough polystyrene surfaces is consistent with the theory of film drainage betweenslippery surfaces. The slip lengths are found to be of the order of the size of asperities, and do not dependon the separation and shear rate. The results are important for colloidal dynamics and nanofluidics.
I. Introduction
Recent years have seen an increase in the number of
devices available to measure interaction forces betweentwo surfaces separated by a thin film. Here we focus onthe atomic force microscope (AFM), which was invented
1
to image the topography of surfaces but is now becomingan important tool for investigating surface interactions.
2
As in the original (static) version of the surface forceapparatus (SFA),
3in the AFM the force is obtained from
the deflection of a measuring spring or cantilever. Whatis different from the SFA, where the cantilever deflectionis detected interferometrically, is that the AFM useselectronic or digitally analyzed optical methods to senseit. Another difference is that various electronic techniquesare used to control the motion of the surface. Besides that,the original AFM data, that is, the deflection versus theposition of the piezo curves, are much more sensitive athigh speed than the SFA separation versus time curves.
4
A corollary of all this is that the AFM is much moreconvenient than the SFA for force measurements at veryhigh speed, that is, for studying the highly dynamicphenomena in a thin gap. Moreover, the AFM forcemeasurements are always dynamic, because we alwaysdeal with dynamic thinning, or 窶彭rainage窶・ of a liquid filmconfined between approaching surfaces, that is, a squeezefilm geometry.
5Therefore, special care should be taken to
approach a quasi-static regime.6Despite these obvious
advantages of the AFM design for studying thin filmdrainage, this technique has only rarely been used forhigh-speed lubrication (drainage) investigations.
7-9In
contrast to this, a number of SFA methods have beendeveloped and successfully applied for this purpose.
4,10 -16
The reason for such an apparent paradox is two compli-
cations connected with the use of the AFM at high speed.First are the 窶徂ardware窶・difficulties, which are mostlydue to the creep and hysteresis of the oscillating piezo, itscalibration, and position control. Second are what we call窶徭oftware窶・complications, caused by difficulties in theinterpretation of experimental data. On one hand, this isthe direct consequence of the 窶徂ardware窶・problems thatlead, for example, to the uncertainty in determining thezero in both separation and force. On the other hand, thisreflects the AFM configuration geometry, where the typicalsize of a colloidal probe is much smaller than the size ofthe cantilever. The complication due to viscous 窶徂ysteresis窶掫as already mentioned in the early reports.
17-19In the
previous paper5of this series we have calculated, both
numerically and analytically, the contribution to the totaldeflection caused by a hydrodynamic drag on the canti-lever, and we demonstrated that it is normally non-negligible.
This paper deals with the quantitative studying of thin
film drainage with the AFM. First we generalize theasymptotic approach developed in ref 5 to the real situation
* Corresponding author. E-mail: vinograd@mpip-mainz.mpg.de.
窶Max Planck Institute for Polymer Research.
窶｡Russian Academy of Sciences.
(1) Binnig, G.; Quate, S. F.; Gerber, C. Phys. Rev. Lett. 1986 ,56, 930.
(2) Ducker, W. A.; Senden, T. J.; Pashley, R. M. Nature 1991 ,353,
239.
(3) Israelachvili, J. N.; Adams, G. E. J. Chem. Soc., Faraday Trans.
11978 ,74, 975.
(4) Chan, D. Y. C.; Horn, R. G. J. Chem. Phys. 1985 ,83, 5311.
(5) Vinogradova, O. I.; Butt, H. J.; Yakubov, G. E.; Feuillebois, F.
Rev. Sci. Instrum. 2001 ,72, 2330.
(6) Ishida, N.; Sakamoto, M.; Miyahara, M.; Higashitani, K. J. Colloid
Interface Sci. 2001 ,235, 190.(7) Butt, H. J.; Do ﾂｨppenschmidt, A.; Hu ﾂｨ ttl, G.; Mu ﾂｨ ller, E.; Vinogradova,
O. I. J. Chem. Phys. 2000 ,113, 1194.
(8) Craig, V. S. J.; Neto, C.; Williams, D. R. M. Phys. Rev. Lett. 2001 ,
87, 054504.
(9) Bonaccurso, E.; Kappl, M.; Butt, H. J. Phys. Rev. Lett. 2002 ,88,
076101.
(10) Israelachvili, J. N. J. Colloid Interface Sci. 1986 ,110, 263.
(11) Lodge, K. B.; Mason, R. Proc. R. Soc. London, A 1982 ,383, 279.
(12) George, J. M.; Millot, S.; Loubet, J. L.; Tonck, A. J. Chem. Phys.
1993 ,98, 7345.
(13) Horn, R. G.; Vinogradova, O. I.; Mackay, M. E.; Phan-Thien, N.
J. Chem. Phys. 2000 ,112, 6424.
(14) Vinogradova, O. I.; Horn, R. G. Langmuir 2001 ,17, 1604.
(15) Zhu, Y.; Granick, S. Phys. Rev. Lett. 2001 ,87, 096105.
(16) Baudry, J.; Charlaix, E.; Tonck, A.; Mazuyer, D. Langmuir 2001 ,
17, 5232.
(17) Hoh, J. H.; Engel, A. Langmuir 1993 ,9, 3310.
(18) O窶儡hea, S. J.; Welland, M. E. Langmuir 1998 ,14, 4186.
(19) Viani, M. B.; Scha ﾂｨffer, T. E.; Chand, A.; Rief, M.; Gaub, H. E.;
Hansma, P. K. J. Appl. Phys. 1999 ,86, 2258.1227 Langmuir 2003, 19,1227 -1234
10.1021/la026419f CCC: $25.00 ﾂｩ 2003 American Chemical Society
Published on Web 01/23/2003
Downloaded via KYUSHU UNIV on May 3, 2023 at 08:58:32 (UTC).
See https://pubs.acs.org/sharingguidelines for options on how to legitimately share published articles.

of AFM force measurements, and we incorporate the
deflection due to hydrodynamic pressure on the cantileverto the AFM force balance. One question of interest is howto subtract accurately the contribution of viscous drag onthe cantilever to the total cantilever deflection. Anotheris how to analyze the remaining concentrated force actingon a colloidal probe. Second, we describe the dynamic forcemeasurements with a new AFM-related setup, which isfree from the usual AFM 窶徂ardware窶・problems. Third, wepresent the results of such measurements for two systems.As an initial application of the experimental techniqueand theoretical method, we have chosen to study silicaand polystyrene surfaces immersed in aqueous electrolytesolutions. Extensions of our method to study other systemswould be straightforward.
II. Theoretical Modeling
For the sake of brevity, only a condensed description of
the theory and main ideas is given here. Some of the detailsare presented in Appendices.
A. Limiting Expressions for Deflection of the AFM
Cantilever. First, we summarize and extend earlier
relationships for the deflection of a tilted cantilever (assketched in Figure 1) which are pertinent to the presentanalysis.
5We consider a rectangular cantilever of width
wand length L(assuming )w/L,1). In other words,
we limit ourselves to asymptotic expressions, which caneasily be handled.
20However, here we do not apply the
limitation of a small tilt angle, as done previously.5Onereason is the relatively large tilt angle of the commercial
setups (13ﾂｰ at the Nanoscope (Digital Instrumental) and11ﾂｰ in the Molecular Force Probe (Asylum Research), forexample). Another reason is that a large tilt angle can beused to minimize the contribution to the deflection fromthe viscous flow on the cantilever.
A Vertical Force at the End Only, No Drag on the
Cantilever. The force Fis negative for an attractive
interaction and positive in the case of repulsion. If (d z/
dx)
2,1, then the relation between the bending moment
due to the elastic response of a cantilever and its curvatureis described as
where Iis the moment of inertia and Eis Young窶冱 modulus.
The bending moment is also equal to a torque about the
point at x, exerted by the applied force
where Ris the tilt angle.
Combining eqs 1 and 2, we derive a differential equation
for the shape of the cantilever
The boundary conditions express the fact that both
position and slope are fixed at one end
This gives us the cantilever shape
and the deflection due to a concentrated force at the end
is given by
where k)3EI/L
3is the spring constant.
In the first-order approximation, the deflection of a
cantilever due to a concentrated force at the end does notdepend on the small tilt angle ( Rf0), because in this case
eq 6 is reduced to
ﾂ｢z(1)(L))F/k, the equation which is
normally used to relate a deflection to a force. An importantpoint to note is that the use of this simplified equationdoes not really affect the results of equilibrium forcemeasurements. Indeed, for a tilt angle of 11ﾂｰ (MolecularForce Probe) the force is underestimated only by 2.8%,and for a tilt angle of 13ﾂｰ (Nanoscope) it is only under-estimated by 3.9%. This mistake can be treated as small.
A Distributed Normal Pressure Only. In the dynamic
force experiment the cantilever width and the gap betweena cantilever and substrate could be of the same order,which could lead to a complicated description of the flow.However, approximate expressions for the drag force cannevertheless be written, as was suggested previously fortwo spheres,
22by simply adding the drag force calculated
from Stokes flow on an isolated body and Reynolds flow(20) We clarify our point of view by using the simplest case of a
rectangular cantilever. In reality, the cantilevers are often V-shaped.The parallel beam approximation
40is commonly used as a model of
V-shaped AFM cantilevers in analytical evaluations of the springconstant. Such a model, being applied to the calculation of thehydrodynamic behavior of the cantilever, would lead to the verycumbersome calculations. One can, however, use another approach,based on the fact that the only combination having the dimension ofa force is ﾃｭvD, where Dis some characteristic size of the body. This
means that for a thin gap the drag force can be expressed as F
ﾃｭvDfunction( D/H,D窶ｲ/H), where D窶ｲis some characteristic size. One
can, therefore, suggest that the deflection of a real V-shaped cantileverwill be determined by the equations derived in this paper, providedthat Lis still the cantilever length but wis some appropriately chosen
effective width. An important point to note is that for the V-shapedcantilevers the approximation of a narrow cantilever will often not bevalid. Therefore, the use of such cantilevers would require a morecomplicated numerical approach.
5(21) Neto, C.; Craig, V. S. J. Langmuir 2001 ,17, 2097.
(22) Barnocky, G.; Davis, R. H. J. Colloid Interface Sci. 1988 ,121,
226.
Figure 1. AFM cantilever deflected due to a concentrated force
at one end and a nonuniform hydrodynamic pressure along thelength of the cantilever.M)EId2z
dx2(1)
M)F(LcosR-x) (2)
F(LcosR-x))EId2z
dx2(3)
z(0))0,z窶ｲ(0))-sinR (4)
ﾂ｢z(1)(x))z(x)+xsinR)F
EI(Lx2cosR
2-x3
6)(5)
ﾂ｢z(1)(L))F
2k(-1+3 cos R) (6)1228 Langmuir, Vol. 19, No. 4, 2003 Vinogradova and Yakubov

for a thin gap. By its definition, the first force gives a
deflection which is independent of the gap.
Here we first focus on the lubrication (Reynolds) flow.
In the lubrication approximation, the Navier -Stokes
equation gives
where vt){vx;vy}is the tangential component of the fluid
velocity and rt){@/@x;@/@y}. In this notation, the
continuity equation is
where vzis the normal component of the velocity field. We
have to solve the system of differential equations (eqs 7and 8) with the boundary conditions
with the deflection
ﾂ｢z(2))ﾂ｢z(2)(x,t). Here H(t)i st h e
minimum gap between substrate and a cantilever. We
further assume ﾂ｢z(2)>0 and v<0 for a substrate moving
in the zdirection.
The assumption ,1 and estimates of the orders of
magnitude allow further simplification ( rt@/@y)t ob e
made to give an analytical solution of eqs 7 and 8. Takinginto account that p)0 at both y)0 and y)w, we derive
where
is the gap between the substrate and a deflected cantilever.
In eq 10 one can safely omit
ﾂ｢z(2). This can be justified
provided the deflection is small, that is, when ﾂ｢z(2),H+
sinR(L-x). This is the typical experimental situation,
because the deflection of the cantilever is usually lessthan 200 nm, while the minimum possible separation H
2R, where 2 R)3-10ﾃｭm is the typical diameter of the
attached sphere. In fact, in some resent experiments evenlarger spheres were used.
8,9,21Therefore, the bending
moment is expressed as
The final integro-differential equation for a cantilever
shape ﾂ｢(x,t)i s
with the boundary conditionsThe governing equations for cantilever shape can be
further simplified if the velocity of deflection ﾂ｢ﾅ奴(2)is small
compared with the speed of piezo v(In previous work5we
have also made such an assumption). This limitation leadsto an analytical solution for the deflection of the cantileverend:
with
where ﾃｧ)H/(LsinR). The dimensionless function
ﾃｧ1/has
been interpreted as a correction for tilt angle between thesurfaces in the expression for the deflection of a narrowhorizontal cantilever. It follows from eq 14 that the viscousdrag on the cantilever cannot change as strongly withdistance as H
-3. However, this limiting case can be
expected only when ﾃｧ.1. Taking into account that H/L
is always ,1, this asymptotic form is easily violated even
for very small R. Hence, in contrast to the deflection due
to a concentrated force at the end of the cantilever, thedeflection due to the distributed hydrodynamic pressureis sensitive to the tilt angle Reven when it is small.
The approximation is justified (see Appendix A) provided
that
This inequality is valid in the typical AFM force dynamic
experiment.
The deflection due to Stokes flow could be presented as
In this expression Ais a fitting parameter which depends
on the cantilever geometry.
B. Force Balance. The AFM force balance should
incorporate both the (concentrated) force on the sphereand the drag on the cantilever.
Assuming ﾂ｢
z)ﾂ｢z(1)+ﾂ｢z(2)+ﾂ｢z(3), the force balance
corresponding to the dynamic force measurements can bewritten as
C. Concentrated Forces Acting on the Sphere. The
forces acting on the sphere may be treated as concentratedin the scale of our problem. In the dynamic AFMexperiment these are hydrodynamic and surface forces,that is
The hydrodynamic force can be written as
22
where his the distance between the sphere and substrate,rtpﾃｭ@2vt
@z2(7)
@vz
@z+rtvt)0 (8)
Atz)-xsinR+ ﾂ｢z(2): vz)ﾂ｢ﾅ奴(2),vt)0
Atz)-(LsinR+H): vz)-Hﾅ・ - v,vt)0
p)6ﾃｭy(y-w)(v+ﾂ｢ﾅ奴(2))
D3(9)
D)D(x,t))H+sinR(L-x)+ﾂ｢z(2)(10)
M(x,t))s0wsxLp(x窶ｲ,y)(x窶ｲ-x)dydx窶ｲ)-ﾃｭw3[v
2 sin R
(1
H2-1
(H+(L-x)sin R)2)+sxL ﾂ｢ﾅ奴(2)(x,t)dx
(H+(L-x)sin R)3]
(11)
@2ﾂ｢z(2)
@x2)3M
kL3(12)ﾂ｢z(2)(0,t))0,@ﾂ｢z(2)(0,t)
@x)0,@ﾂ｢z(2)(0,t)
@t)0 (13)
ﾂ｢z(2)(L))z(L)+sinRL)-3vﾃｭL
8k(w
H)3
ﾃｧ1/(14)
ﾃｧ1/)4ﾃｧ
3[1-3ﾃｧ
2+3ﾃｧ2-3ﾃｧ3ln(1+1
ﾃｧ)](15)
ﾂ｢ﾅ奴(2)/v-3vﾃｭ
8ksinR(w
H)3
,1
ﾂ｢ﾅ奴(3)-3vﾃｭLA
8k
ﾂ｢z)F
2k(-1+3 cos R)-3vﾃｭL
8k[(w
H)3
ﾃｧ1/+A](16)
F)Fh+Fs (17)
Fh)-6ﾃｭﾃｰRdh
dt(1+R
hf*)(18)Dynamic Effects on Force Measurements Langmuir, Vol. 19, No. 4, 2003 1229

andf* is the correction for deviations from the Reynolds
flow in the thin gap.
Equation 18 is in agreement with the lubrication force24
forh/R,1 and with the Stokes drag for h/R.1.
We stress that the hydrodynamic drag on a sphere is
proportional to the velocity of the relative motion. In thecase of a bare cantilever, this was approximately equal tothat of the moving substrate v. For an attached sphere,
this simplification is no longer valid, and in the generalcase, the velocity of a sphere relative to the substratedh/dt*v.
One reason for deviations from Reynolds theory could
be liquid slippage over a solid surface (for a review see ref23). The expressions for correction for slippage in the caseof surfaces with different, but constant, slip lengths aregiven in Appendix B.
D. Summary. To finish this section, the deflection of
a cantilever in a dynamic force experiment in the generalcase reflects both a colloidal probe -substrate interaction
and a cantilever -substrate interaction. We have formu-
lated the equations of motion (force balance) that takeboth these effects into account and allow design of alubrication experiment. The important thing to stress isthat the contributions from different terms to the forcebalance have different functional dependences on the mainexperimental parameters. Therefore, they can be sepa-rated/subtracted independently on their absolute valueand/or their ration. Below we present experimental datathat support our theoretical predictions.
III. Experimental Section
The experimental setup was similar to that described in refs
26-28. Cantilevers were fixed in a holder with R5-20ﾂｰ. To
measure the drainage curves, the cuvette was moved verticallytoward the cantilever with a 12 ﾃｭm range piezoelectric translator
(Physik Instrumente, Germany). This translator is equipped withintegrated capacitance position sensors, which provide measure-ments of their actual position and further adjustment of piezomovement. This feature leads to an accuracy of 0.005%, whichmeans that for piezo travel of 12 ﾃｭm the maximum error is 0.6
nm. During the movement the deflection of the cantilever wasmeasured with an optical lever technique. For this, the light ofa laser diode (3 mW, 670 nm) was focused onto the back of thegold coated cantilever using microfocusing optics (spot diameteris about 8 ﾃｭm), and after reflection from the cantilever and from
another mirror the position of the reflected laser spot wasmeasured with a two-dimensional position sensitive detector(PSD) (SiTek, Sweden, active area 2 2c m
2). Drainage curves
were measured in the time range from 20 s to 250 ms per forcecurve. This corresponds to driving speeds from 1 to 20 ﾃｭm/s. To
calculate speed of piezo movement in the case of a triangulardrive function, we simply multiply piezo oscillation frequency bydouble the piezo range distance. To convert the output voltageof the position sensitive device to a deflection in nanometers, wecalculate the slope of the constant compliance line of the forcecurve, where any change in height position is equal to the changein deflection. The result of a force measurement is a plot of thecantilever deflection ﾂ｢
zversus the height position of the piezo
translator.
We use rectangular tipless cantilevers covered with 3 nm of
chromium and 40 nm of gold ( w)52ﾃｭm and L)450 ﾃｭm, which
gives )0.12). The spring constant ( k0.1-0.2 N/m) of the
cantilever was determined by the method of power spectrumdensity of the cantilever thermal noise described in ref 29. To
decrease the hydrodynamic drag of the liquid on the cantileverand in order to vary RandHindependently, we have designed
a 窶徭nowman窶・probe (Figure 2). To fabricate 窶徭nowman窶・probes,glass spheres (Duke Scientific, Palo Alto, CA) of 10 ﾃｭm radius
were attached on the top of the cantilever using epoxy glue andthen clean silica or polystyrene particles (both from Bangs Labs,Fisher, IN) were attached approximately on the top of the glassspheres using epoxy glue or a sintering method. Spheres wereglued with UV-curing Norland optical adhesive No. 81 (NorlandProducts, New Brunswick, NJ). After spheres were attached onthe cantilevers, they were exposed for 10 min under UVirradiation (12 W, ﾃｬ)254 nm) until complete adhesive
solidification. This glue is resistive to most organic solvents,including tetrahydrofuran (Aldrich, Germany) and toluene, whichmeans the lowest level of contamination connected with the glue.After formation of the 窶徭nowman窶・ probes were cleaned in anoxygen plasma for 5 min. Immediately after cleaning, probeswere mounted in the setup and immersed in the experimentalcuvette. After 10 -30 min, cantilever drift normally disappeared
and measurements were performed. The geometric parametersof experiments for further analysis were obtained from analysisof scanning electron microscope (SEM) microphotographs, asshown in Figure 3.
The first pair of interacting surfaces studied was a silica or
a borosilicate glass sphere (Bangs Labs Inc., Carmel, USA) withaverage radius 1.85 and 5.2 ﾃｭm (prepared and attached to a
cantilever as described above) against a silicon wafer cleanedwith the same procedure. All surfaces were considered to behydrophilic and are found to be molecularly smooth. Root-mean-square roughness over a 1 ﾃｭm1ﾃｭm area was in the range 0.3
(23) Vinogradova, O. I. Int. J. Miner. Process. 1999 ,56, 31.
(24) Vinogradova, O. I. Langmuir 1995 ,11, 2213.
(25) Vinogradova, O. I.; Feuillebois, F. J. Colloid Interface Sci. 2000 ,
221,1 .
(26) Yakubov, G. E.; Butt, H. J.; Vinogradova, O. I. J. Phys. Chem.
B2000 ,104, 3407.
(27) Vinogradova, O. I.; Yakubov, G. E.; Butt, H. J. J. Chem. Phys.
2001 ,114, 8124.
(28) Ecke, S.; Raiteri, R.; Bonaccurso, E.; Reiner, C.; Deiseroth, H.
J.; Butt, H. J. Rev. Sci. Instrum. 2001 ,72, 4164. (29) Hutter, J. L.; Bechho ﾂｨfer, J. Rev. Sci. Instrum. 1993 ,64, 1868.
Figure 2. Video microscope image of an AFM cantilever with
the attached colloidal 窶徭nowman窶・probe. The insets showscanning electron microscope images for various glued andsintered 窶徭nowmen窶・
Figure 3. Example of the geometric parameters of the
experiment determined from scanning electron microscopeimages. Sdenotes the 窶徭nowman height窶・230 Langmuir, Vol. 19, No. 4, 2003 Vinogradova and Yakubov

nm for both an individual sphere and a wafer. No indications of
larger asperities or peaks were detected. We treat these surfacesas smooth, because their roughness is of the order of the accuracyof the determination of surface separation. We also consider themto be hydrophilic, because the measurements of the contact angleon the silicon water, done by observation of a sessile drop witha commercial setup (Data Physics, Germany), showed completewetting.
30
The second pair of interacting surfaces was a polystyrene latex
sphere (Bangs Labs Inc., Carmel, USA) of radius 4.38 ﾃｭm against
a polystyrene plate. The preparation of polystyrene surfaces wasdone as before.
27,31Imaging of the polystyrene plate with a regular
AFM tip revealed that it is as smooth as the silica surfaces. Thepolystyrene spheres were found to be significantly rougher, andthe root-mean-square roughness over a 1 ﾃｭm1ﾃｭm area was
in the range 2.2 -2.8 nm. The maximum peak-to-valley height
difference was found to be 15 nm. We therefore treat these spheresas rough. Measurements of the contact angle on the planarpolystyrene surface have given a receding contact angle of 86ﾂｰ.The advancing angle is found to be 92ﾂｰ. The contact angle ofpolystyrene microspheres was determined with a proceduredescribed earlier.
31,32The contact angles measured with different
polystyrene particles varied by (4ﾂｰ from particle to particle. The
average receding contact angle was 68ﾂｰ, and the averageadvancing contact angle was -92ﾂｰ, that is, the same as that for
a polystyrene plate.
Experiments were carried out in 10
-1M (polystyrene) and
10-3M (glass and silica) NaCl (99.99%, Aldrich) aqueous
solutions. Water for solutions was prepared using a commercialMilli-Q system containing ion-exchange and charcoal stages.
IV. Results
The original deflection versus distance curves for a
typical force experiment performed at different speedsare shown in Figure 4 (top). The zero deflection (force)position was determined by invoking symmetry of thehydrodynamic force acting on the system (cantilever andsphere) at large separation during approach and retrac-tion. Surface forces acting on the sphere are, in the generalcase, negligibly small at separations larger than 1 ﾃｭm. In
our case, they can be ignored at distances above 20 nm.Therefore, the zero-deflection position corresponds to themiddle line of the long-range part of the drainage curve.One can see that the absolute value of deflection increaseswith the approaching velocity and decreases with theseparation. This confirms that the total deflection mea-sured in the experiment contains a hydrodynamic con-tribution. The large range of measured deflection suggeststhat the drag on a cantilever plays an important role.
A. Viscous Drag on a Cantilever. We now start with
the analysis of data for the deflection of the cantilever atlong-range distances due to nonuniform hydrodynamicpressure. Measurements presented in Figure 4 (bottom)test the approximate expressions (eq 14) for the deflectiondue to drag on a cantilever. Here we illustrate our approachby using a relatively small tilt angle ( Ris roughly 4ﾂｰ) in
order to have a larger contribution to deflection due toflow around the cantilever. The results of several seriesof measurements are also presented in the scaled form.The scaling is chosen according to eq 14. The results fromseveral experiments suggest that the measurements arein perfect agreement with the theoretical predictions andthat for all the experiments (with this particular config-uration geometry) the Stokes drag can be described bytaking A)36. Therefore, in the subsections below we
present and analyze only the concentrated force acting onthe sphere obtained by subtracting the deflection of the
cantilever from the total deflection measured. The errorwe introduce with such a procedure is mostly due touncertainty in the measurement of the tilt angle ( (1ﾂｰ).
B. Interaction of Smooth Hydrophilic Silica and
Glass Surfaces. The aim of this subsection is to dem-
onstrate that one can make a quantitative analysis of theconcentrated force acting on a sphere. As a first step, theprocedure includes the DLVO fit for simple simple silicaand glass systems at low speed. One question of interestis, 窶弩hen can the AFM force measurements be treated asa quasiequilibrium?窶・In other words, 窶弩hich speed can beconsidered to be slow enough to avoid a dynamic contri-bution to the deflection versus position curve?窶・It followsfrom our results that a speed below 1 ﾃｭm/s can normally
be treated as slow. There is no speed dependence of thetotal deflection at vbelow 1 ﾃｭm/s, but a higher speed of
a piezo translator gives different results for differentspeeds, which indicates a contribution from hydrodynamicdrag. At low speed the force is exponentially decayingwith a decay length equal to the Debye length for ourelectrolyte solution (in all these experiments we used 10
-3
M solutions). The parameters of this double layer repulsion
Fshave been obtained from measurements at speed 0.1
ﾃｭm/s for every given pair of interacting surfaces. We also
remark that these quasi static force measurements have(30) Unfortunately, to our knowledge, there is no routine way of
making contact angle measurements on hydrophilic microspheres.
(31) Yakubov, G. E.; Vinogradova, O. I.; Butt, H. J. Colloid J. 2001 ,
63, 518.
(32) Yakubov, G. E.; Vinogradova, O. I.; Butt, H. J. J. Adhesion Sci.
Technol. 2001 ,14, 1783.
Figure 4. Total cantilever deflection in the dynamic AFM force
experiment ( R)5.0(0.5ﾂｰ). (top) Original data obtained at the
driving speeds (20ﾃｭm/s (1), (15ﾃｭm/s (2), and (10ﾃｭm/s (3).
The experiment was performed with a 1.9 ﾃｭm snowman probe
(窶徭nowman height窶・is 14.0 ﾃｭm). (bottom) Set of different
measurements presented in the scaled form: scaled deflection
is-8ﾂ｢z/(3kvﾃｭL); scaled distance is ﾃｧ1/(w/H)3. Approach speed
varied from -6t o-20ﾃｭm/s; the 窶徭nowman heights窶・and sphere
radii were from 10.4 ﾃｭm to 15.2 ﾃｭm, and from 1.9 ﾃｭmt o5 . 4 ﾃｭm,
correspondingly. The straight line has the slope 窶・窶・(窶・-1窶・for
the retraction part of the curve). The negative and positive窶徘eaks窶・correspond to the regions close to the initial distanceand contact. These regions have been excluded from the analysisof a flow on cantilever, because here its deflection is not solelydue to a drag force on it.Dynamic Effects on Force Measurements Langmuir, Vol. 19, No. 4, 2003 1231

revealed neither any hysteresis between approach and
retraction data nor an adhesion peak.
Figure 5 shows the original drainage data obtained at
different driving speeds and a scaled hydrodynamic force.Two ways have been used to analyze the hydrodynamicforce. The first algorithm was similar to that usedpreviously in the SFA experiment
4,13and included a
numerical solution of the differential equation (eq 17) fora concentrated force to fit the experimental data. In thisprocedure we used the experimentally measured valuesofR,h,k,A, and parameters of the double layer force,
obtained from low-speed measurements. Then, performingthe least-squares fit of data for a concentrated force, weobtain the slip lengths b
1andb2for interacting surfaces.
The second algorithm was based on subtracting the doublelayer force from the total force acting on the sphere andon a subsequent analysis of F
h, by assuming it is described
by eq 18. This analysis included a calculation of f* for a
given h, and a least-squares fit of this correction for
slippage to get b1andb2. It was found that both approaches
lead to the same results. The main conclusion made from
the inspection of experimental data (see Figure 5) is thatno slippage ( b
1)b2)0(1 nm) is observed within the
experimental accuracy. The important point to note isthat the large sphere of the 窶徭nowman窶・configuration doesnot implicate our results. Rough estimates of the possiblecontribution of such a sphere are given in Appendix C.The substitution of typical experimental values to eq 20suggests that the contribution from the large 窶徭nowman窶捏phere never exceeds 5% of the drag acting on the smallsphere in the lubrication regime. This is confirmed by thefact that the same results (i.e. no slip) are obtained bothfor a silica sphere of radius 1.85 ﾃｭm of the 窶徭nowman窶・
probe and for a borosilicate glass sphere of radius 5.2 ﾃｭm
attached to a cantilever. Our experiment, therefore, doesnot confirm the recent statement,
9made for a similar
system (borosilicate sphere of R)10ﾃｭm against a silicone
wafer), that the smooth hydrophilic surface is character-ized by a rate dependent slip length of the order of 10 nm.Unfortunately, we cannot comment more about thereasons for such a discrepancy, because a lot of the detailsof analysis are omitted in that publication.
In summary, our results for smooth hydrophilic surfaces
are in excellent agreement with the Reynolds theory ofhydrodynamic lubrication with no-slip boundary condi-tions. It would be useful to those interested in measuringhydrodynamic forces to have some feeling about therelative contribution of different terms to the totaldeflection described by eq 16. We are now in a position toestimate it. Table 1 illustrates how important the differentterms could be depending on the driving speed andseparation. One can see that, for the high speed experi-ment, the contribution due to the cantilever is indeedsignificant and has to be subtracted by using our modeland a large distance fit, as suggested here. At low speedthe contribution from flow on a cantilever can safely beignored, and the deflection is mostly due to colloidal forces.However, even at such a speed there could be somecontribution from the hydrodynamic force on the sphereacting at separations of a few nanometers.
C. Interaction of Rough Hydrophobic Polystyrene
Surfaces. The quasi-equilibrium colloidal interactions
between hydrophobic polystyrene surfaces have beenstudied before.
27,35It was found that two types of interac-
tion in such a system are possible. One is observed onlyin dilute solutions and is of electrostatic origin.
27An-
other27,35is characterized by an abrupt long-range jump
of the surfaces into contact due to formation of nanobub-bles
36-39at the rough hydrophobic surface of polystyrene
spheres. Here we focus only on the drainage behavior of
(33) Vinogradova, O. I. Langmuir 1998 ,14, 2827.
(34) Vinogradova, O. I. Langmuir 1996 ,12, 5963.
(35) Considine, R. F.; Hayes, R. A.; Horn, R. G. Langmuir 1999 ,15,
1657.
(36) Vinogradova, O. I.; Bunkin, N. F.; Churaev, N. V.; Kiseleva, O.
A.; Lobeyev, A. V.; Ninham, B. W. J. Colloid Interface Sci. 1995 ,173,
443.
(37) Bunkin, N. F.; Lobeyev, A. V.; Movchan, T. G.; Ninham, B. W.;
Vinogradova, O. I. Langmuir 1997 ,13, 3024.
(38) Ishida, N.; Inoue, T.; Miyahara, N.; Higashitani, K. Langmuir
2000 ,16, 6377.
(39) Tyrell, J. W. G.; Attard, P. Langmuir 2002 ,18, 160.
(40) Sader, J. E. Rev. Sci. Instrum. 1995 ,66, 4583.
Figure 5. Hydrodynamic force acting on the hydrophilic
spheres. (top) Original force vs distance data obtained with a5.2ﾃｭm probe at the driving speed -20ﾃｭm/s (triangles), and a
theoretical curve obtained by numerical solution of the forcebalance equation (solid curve). (bottom) Scaled hydrodynamicforce -F
h/(6ﾃｰﾃｭdh/dt)-1 plotted against R/h. Driving speed
was -20ﾃｭm/s (curves 1 and 3) and -10ﾃｭm/s (curves 2 and 4);
cantilever sample distances (1, 2 -10.4 ﾃｭm; 3, 4 -14.0 ﾃｭm);
sphere窶冱 radii (1, 2 -5.2ﾃｭm; 3, 4 -1.9ﾃｭm). The slope of the solid
line is equal to f*)1.Table 1. Contribution from Different Terms to the
Deflection of a Cantilever in a Typical High-Speed
Experiment (Borosilicate Glass Sphere of R)5.2ﾃｭm)a
h,n m ﾂ｢z,n m ﾂ｢z(1),n m ﾂ｢z(2)+ﾂ｢z(3),n m
v)20ﾃｭm/s
3000 2.3 2.31000 2.7 0.1 2.6
100 3.8 1.0 2.8
20 8.1 1.3 3.9 2.9
5 17.2 6.2 8.2 2.9
v)1ﾃｭm/s
3000 0.1 0.11000 0.1 0.1
100 0.2 0.1 0.1
20 1.6 1.3 0.2 0.1
5 6.8 6.1 0.5 0.1
aIn the column for ﾂ｢z(1)the numbers on the left correspond to a
contribution from a surface force, and the numbers on the right toa contribution from a hydrodynamic force.1232 Langmuir, Vol. 19, No. 4, 2003 Vinogradova and Yakubov

this system, where the attractive surface interaction is
mediated by nanobubbles. Due to complicated analysis ofdouble layer forces in such a system, we here use only10
-1M solution and are therefore in the situation when
the double layer forces are of much shorter range andweaker than hydrodynamic drag.
Figure 6 presents the results obtained in several series
of measurements. Presentation of the results in scaledform clearly demonstrates that drainage is faster thanthat for the hydrophilic case even before the jump intocontact. The analysis of data was performed in a waysimilar to what we used in the previous subsection. Thebest fit was provided when the values of the slip lengthswere constant and confined between the pairs b
1)10(
1 nm against b2)0.5(1 nm, and b1)b2)4(1 nm.
In other words, the drainage of a thin film confinedbetween hydrophobic rough polystyrene surfaces is inagreement with the theory of film drainage betweenslippery surfaces,
24and the slip lengths are of the order
of the size of asperities. Whether this is a consequence ofroughness itself, or nanobubble formation on a roughhydrophobic surface, remains an open question which will
be studied in future publications. Our current approachdoes not allow us to draw any further conclusions aboutthe origin of slippage in polystyrene systems.Acknowledgment. We thank Franc ﾃｼois Feuillebois for
helpful suggestions that led to Appendix A, and GunnarGlasser for making SEM images.
Appendix A: Assumption of Small Deflection
Velocity
The assumption that led to eq 14 is that the deflection
velocity is small as compared with v,o r
ﾂ｢ﾅ奴(2)v,1. We will
now check under which experimental conditions this isindeed true and if this condition is equivalent to a conditionof a small deflection, which is always valid.
Taking the time derivative of
ﾂ｢z(2), we find
with
One can show that ﾂ｡ﾃｧ3)O(1) for realistic values of
ﾃｧ. Therefore,
Using typical numerical values of experiment, we get
ﾂ｢ﾅ奴(2)/v10-4; that is, the deflection velocity is indeed
small.
Appendix B: Correction for Slippage in the
Equations for a Viscous Drag on a Sphere
In the case of surfaces with different, but constant, slip
lengths b1)b)ﾃ｢handb2)b(K+1))ﾃ｢h(K+1), where
Kcan have values between -1 and竏・ it takes the form24,25
with
We note that, due to a misprint, the factor 2 in the first
term of case iii was lost in ref 24 (and corrected in ref 25).This, however, did not affect the limiting expression for
Figure 6. Hydrodynamic force acting between hydrophobic
polystyrene surfaces. (top) Original force vs distance dataobtained with a 4.9 ﾃｭm probe (triangles) (driving speed -20
ﾃｭm/s) against a polystyrene surface. The solid curve corresponds
to the theoretical calculations for symmetric cases with sliplength 4 nm. The dotted arrow shows jump into a contact.(bottom) Scaled concentrated hydrodynamic force [ F
h/(6ﾃｰﾃｭdh/
dt)-1] acting on the hydrophobic polystyrene spheres plotted
against R/h. Driving speed was -20ﾃｭm/s (curves 1 and 3) and
-10ﾃｭm/s (2); 窶徭nowman heights窶・were 13.3 ﾃｭm (1, 2) and 12.4
ﾃｭm (3); small sphere radii were 4.9 ﾃｭm (1, 2), 4.4 ﾃｭm (3), and
1.9ﾃｭm (4). The solid line corresponds to the no-slip case. The
dashed line corresponds to a slip case with the slip length 4 nm.The dotted arrow shows jump into a contact.ﾂ｢ﾅ奴(2)
v)-3ﾃｭvw3ﾂ｡
8kL3sin4R
ﾂ｡)-2
3ﾃｧ+4-3ﾃｧ2-6ﾃｧ3
ﾃｧ3(ﾃｧ+1)-4l n(1+1
ﾃｧ)
ﾂ｢ﾅ奴(2)
v-3vﾃｭ
8ksinR(w
H)3
(i)Kf-1
f*)1
4(1+3ﾃ｢2ﾃ｢1
4ﾃ｢[(1+1
4ﾃ｢)ln(1 +4ﾃ｢)-1])
(ii)Kf竏・
f*)1
4ﾃ｢2ﾃ｢1
3ﾃ｢[(1+1
3ﾃ｢)ln(1 +3ﾃ｢)-1]
(iii)K*-1,K*竏・
f*)-2x1
ﾃ｢x2x3-2
ﾃ｢2(x3-x2)[(ﾃ｢x2+1)(x2-x1)
x22ln(1 +
ﾃ｢x2)-(ﾃ｢x3+1)(x3-x1)
x32ln(1 +ﾃ｢x3)](B1)
x1)2+K
x2)2(2+K+x1+K+K2)
x3)2(2+K-x1+K+K2)Dynamic Effects on Force Measurements Langmuir, Vol. 19, No. 4, 2003 1233

Kf0 derived in ref 24 and intensively used during the
last few years.9,13,15,16
Appendix C: Estimate of the Hydrodynamic
Interaction between the Large Sphere of the
窶彜nowman窶・and Substrate
The presence of the large 窶徭nowman窶・sphere of radius
R2can contribute to the deflection of the cantilever,
because this sphere can interact hydrodynamically withthe substrate. Determination of the exact amount of thishydrodynamic interaction would require a complicatedthree-dimensional Stokes flow problem. We can neverthe-less give an estimate of this effect by using the simplifiedapproach suggested in ref 5. The main assumption is thatatreR
1the flow is blocked by the small sphere of radius
R1, but at r>R2the flow is not affected by the attached
sphere.
The standard consideration (see, for example, ref 34)
leads to the following differential equation for pressurep
where H)h+r
2/2R2. Then the assumption d p/dr)0a tr)R1leads to
The expression for a force is given by
where h1)h+R12/2R2. The integration gives
with A1)R1/R2<1 and A2)R1/h)R1/(h*+2R1)1/2.
IfA1,1, the equation for a force can be further simplify
and give
LA026419Fd
dr(H3rdp
dr))12ﾃｭvrp)3ﾃｭvR2
H2+3ﾃｭvR12
h3[h2
2H2+ln(1-h
H)+h
H]
Fh)2ﾃｰR2sh1竏柝dH
Fh)6ﾃｰﾃｭvR22
h(1+A1A2[A1A2
2ln(1+2
A1A2)-1])(C1)
Fh3ﾃｭﾃｰvR22
R1(1-R1
2R2)1234 Langmuir, Vol. 19, No. 4, 2003 Vinogradova and Yakubov



================================================================================
File: Bonaccurso et al. 2002 - Hydrodynamic force measurements - boundary slip of water on hydrophilic surfaces and electrokinetic effects.pdf
================================================================================
Number of pages: 4
VOLUME 88, N UMBER 7 PHYSICAL REVIEW LETTERS 1 8F EBRUARY 2002
Hydrodynamic Force Measurements: Boundary Slip of Water
on Hydrophilic Surfaces and Electrokinetic Effects
Elmar Bonaccurso, Michael Kappl, and Hans-Jﾃｼrgen Butt*
Physikalische Chemie II, Universitﾃ､t Siegen, 57068 Siegen, Germany
(Received 11 June 2001; published 1 February 2002)
The hydrodynamic drainage force of aqueous medium between smooth hydrophilic surfaces was mea-
sured with the colloidal probe technique up to shear rates of typically 104s21. Measured force curves
were compared to simulations. To reach agreement between experimental and simulated force curves,
the hydrodynamic force had to be ・》ted with a model allowing for boundary slippage. Boundary slip was
characterized by a slip length of 89nm. Force measurements with charged surfaces could be simulated
taking only hydrodynamic and electrostatic double-layer forces into account.
DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevLett.88.076103 PACS numbers: 68.08.De, 47.20.窶徒, 68.37.Ps, 82.65.+r
The structure and mechanical properties of ・Ｖids at solid
surfaces is important in many phenomena such as lubrica-tion, adhesion, wetting, colloidal hydrodynamics, and mi-
cro・Ｖidics. In ・Ｖid mechanics, one usually relies on the
assumption that, when liquid ・Ｐws over a solid surface,the liquid molecules adjacent to the solid are stationaryrelative to the solid and that the viscosity is equal to thebulk viscosity. Though this might be a good assumption
for macroscopic systems, it is questionable at molecular
dimensions. Measurements with the surface forces appa-ratus (SFA) [1窶・] and computer simulations [4窶・] showedthat the viscosity of simple liquids can increase by manyorders of magnitude, or even undergo a liquid-to-solid tran-
sition, when they are con・］ed between solid walls sepa-
rated only few molecular diameters. Several experimentsindicated that also isolated solid surfaces induce a layeringin an adjacent liquid and that the mechanical properties ofthe ・〉st molecular layers are different from the bulk prop-erties [7窶・0]. The change in the mechanical properties
can be characterized by the position of the plane of shear.
Simple liquids often show a shear plane which is typi-cally 3窶・ molecular diameters away from the solid-liquidinterface.
Most of the experiments have been done for wetting ・Ｖ-
ids. For nonwetting ・Ｖids slippage was observed [11窶・4].
Computer simulation con・〉med that for low ・Ｖid-wallinteractions slippage occurs [15窶・7]. The hydrodynamicboundary condition to describe slippage is [18] n
S/H33527
bdnx/H20862dz. Here, nSis the slip velocity, dnx/H20862dzis the local
shear rate, and bis the slip length. The slip length is the
distance behind the interface at which the liquid velocity
extrapolates to zero. There are, however, exceptions: Pitet al. observed slip with hexadecane on wetted sapphire
surfaces [19]. Craig et al. inferred slip from force mea-
surements with partially hydrophilic surfaces (advancing
contact angle 70
ﾂｱ) in aqueous sucrose solutions [20].
In this paper, we describe results of hydrodynamic force
measurements between hydrophilic surfaces (mica andglass) in an aqueous medium using the colloidal probetechnique. The hydrodynamic force depends critically onthe boundary condition between the liquid and the solid
surfaces. Thus, by ・》ting measured force-versus-distancecurves (from now on called 窶彷orce curves窶・ with appro-
priate models, the boundary condition could be inferred.
Signi・…ant slip was found for water even on hydrophilicsurfaces.
Another purpose of this study was to check for electro-
kinetic effects in force measurements. Electrokinetic ef-
fects arise when a polar liquid ・Ｐws over a charged solid
surface. When dealing with particles, the shear of the liq-uid at charged surfaces leads to electroviscous forces [21].Electroviscous forces were measured directly as a lift forceacting on a particle moving parallel to a charged ・Ｂt sur-
face [22]. In force measurements with the colloidal probe
technique, the particle approaches a wall in a normal di-rection. The liquid is drained out of the closing gap. De-pending on the approaching velocity, high shear rates canoccur. This might lead to an 窶彳lectrokinetic effect窶・in thesense that the effective viscosity in the electric double layer
increases [23].
To detect electrokinetic effects three types of experi-
ments were done.
(i) 窶廩ydrodynamic窶・force curves F
hywere recorded
with high approaching velocities. High salt concentrations
(200 mM monovalent salt, pH 5) were used so that the
electrostatic double-layer force was negligible. Therefore,for distances h.2nm, the total interaction was purely
hydrodynamic.
(ii) 窶廢lectrostatic窶・force curves F
eswere recorded at low
approaching velocity (negligible hydrodynamic force) in
2 mM monovalent salt and a pH around 11. Under these
conditions, the electrostatic double-layer force dominatessince the surfaces of borosilicate glass and mica are nega-tively charged and the Debye length is large (6.8 nm).
(iii) 窶廢lectrokinetic窶・force curves F
ekwere recorded
at high approaching velocities and a strong electric force
(2 mM monovalent salt, pH 11). Electrokinetic force
curves were compared to simulated force curves, takingthe electrostatic double-layer force and the hydrodynamicforce into account.
076103-1 0031-9007 /H2086202/H2086288(7) /H20862076103(4)$20.00 ﾂｩ 2002 The American Physical Society 076103-1
VOLUME 88, N UMBER 7 PHYSICAL REVIEW LETTERS 1 8F EBRUARY 2002
All experiments were done with the particle interaction
apparatus which was described previously [24]. Sphericalborosilicate glass particles (Duke Scienti ・… Corporation,
Palo Alto, California) were sintered to atomic force mi-
croscope (AFM) cantilevers. We used particles with radii
R/H3352710mm to avoid an in ・Ｖence of the cantilever on the
distance-dependent hydrodynamic force [25]. Rectangularcantilevers (length L/H33527210mm, width w/H3352752.5mm)
made of silicon dioxide ( 1.0mm thick, spring constant
K/H333600.056 N/H20862m) and polycrystalline silicon ( 0.5mm
thick, K/H333600.012 N/H20862m) were speci ・…ally designed and
produced (IMM, Germany). Spring constants of canti-levers were calibrated according to Sader et al. [26]. To
measure force curves, a particle was positioned a few
mm above the mica surface in a Te ・Ｐn cuvette which was
・〕led with aqueous electrolyte. Then the mica surface
was periodically moved up and down at constant velocityn
0with a 12mm range piezoelectric translator (Physik
Instrumente, Germany, integrated position sensors, maxi-
maln0:70mm/H20862s). The de ・Ｆction of the cantilever was
measured with an optical lever technique. Therefore, lightof a laser diode was passed through a w aveguide (to ob-
tain a rotational symmetric spot) and focused onto theback of the cantilever. The position of the re ・Ｆcted laser
spot is measured with a position sensitive device (United
Detectors, UK, active area 30330mm
2). Cantilever de-
・Ｆction was recorded as a function of piezo displacement.
A force curve is calculated by multiplying cantilever de-・Ｆction with the spring constant of the cantilever to obtain
the force, and adding piezo displacement and cantilever
de・Ｆction to obtain the distance from contact. The reso-
lution is practically limited by the thermal noise of thecantilever, which in our case was below 0.3 nm, and theuncertainty in determining zero distance. Since the samplewas hard compared to the stiffness of the cantilever the
error in zero distance is probably negligible.
Two typical hydrodynamic force curves recorded at
n
0/H335274mm/H20862s and 40mm/H20862s are shown in Fig. 1. At
high velocities even at large distances, the Stokes frictioncaused a de ・Ｆction of the cantilever which did not depend
on the distance. Stokes friction increased linearly with
the velocity n
0. When applying the Stokes equation of a
sphere F/H335276phR/H11569n0, we derive an effective radius R/H11569
for the cantilever/particle of about 52mm. Here, his the
viscosity of the liquid.
When the particle approaches the mica surface the
repulsive force increases. This hydrodynamic distance-
dependent repulsion increases with increasing approachingvelocity. When retracting the particle with a low velocity,usually the particle adhered to the sample and an adhesionforce had to be overcome. At high retracting velocities,
a stronger apparent attraction is observed because an ad-
ditional hydrodynamic force has to be overcome. Beforethe particle can retract, the liquid has to ・〕l the widening
gap between the particle and the ・Ｂt surface.
We compared the experimental results with theoretical
models. Calculations were ・〉st done with a no-slip condi-
FIG. 1. Hydrodynamic force-versus-distance curves measured
at low velocity ( n0/H335274mm/H20862s,/H17005) and high velocity ( n0/H33527
40mm/H20862s,/H17033) in aqueous electrolyte (200 mM NaCl, pH5 )o n
mica. The force was normalized by dividing it by the radius of
the glass particle R/H3352710mm. Only each 15th point is shown.
Approaching and retracting parts of force curves are indicated
by arrows. Simulations calculated according to Eq. (2) without
(f/H11569/H335271, dashed line) and with slip ( b/H335278.6nm, continuous
line) are plotted. Positive forces are repulsive; negative forces
attractive.
tion which leads to a hydrodynamic force of [7,27] Fhy/H33527
26phR2/H20862h?dh/H20862dt. Here, dh/H20862dtis the real velocity. In
a second calculation, slippage was allowed by introducinga correction factor f
/H11569according to Vinogradova [28]:
Fhy/H3352726phR2
hdh
dtf/H11569
f/H11569/H33527h
3b竏堕ｵ
11h
6b竏・
lnﾂｵ
116b
h竏・
21竏・
.(1)
Both models assume creeping ・Ｐw, Newtonian ・Ｖids, and
small distances ( hﾃｸR).
Hydrodynamic force curves were simulated by solving
the equation of motion for a sphere moving towards a ・Ｂt
surface. Neglecting other surface forces, the hydrodynamicforce is balanced by the restoring force of the cantilever;F
K/H33527K/H20849h2h01n 0t/H20850. Here, h0is the initial separation
att/H335270. The expression h2h01n 0tis equal to the de-
・Ｆction of the cantilever. The effect of the hydrodynamic
force is to retard the particle. As a consequence, the ve-
locity of the particle at a given time tis not equal to n0
because the changing de ・Ｆction of the cantilever has to be
taken into account. This results in a nonuniform velocityof the particle during approach and retraction. The equa-
tion of motion, F
h/H33527FK, was calculated separately for the
approaching and the retracting parts:
26phR2
hdh
dtf/H11569/H33527邃ｦ
K/H20849h2h01n 0t/H20850for approach
K/H20849h2hr2n 0t/H20850for retraction .
(2)
The position of the piezo at the beginning of the retraction
washr. Equation (2) was solved numerically.
076103-2 076103-2
VOLUME 88, N UMBER 7 PHYSICAL REVIEW LETTERS 1 8F EBRUARY 2002
Force curves simulated with the no-slip boundary
condition /H20849f/H11569/H335271/H20850deviated signi ・…antly from measured
force curves, especially at distances below 50 nm (Fig. 1).
Even when introducing an additional prefactor to allow
for possible inaccuracies in RorK, no agreement was
achieved. When correcting for slip and simulating forcecurves with Eq. (2), calculations agreed with experimentalforce curves. Slip lengths of b/H335278
9nm were obtained
independent of n0. We would like to point out that, ex-
cept for the slip length, all parameters were determinedindependently.
The experimental results lead to the conclusion that
boundary slip occurs for water on mica and/or glass. This
opposes the current view about the structure and mechani-
cal properties of water on hydrophilic surfaces. We donot have a good explanation and can discuss only possiblehints for the discrepancy. The occurrence of a signi ・…ant
slip length does not necessarily imply slip on the molecu-lar scale. It could also be a hint for a reduced viscosity.
If the viscosity of the liquid in a surface layer of thick-
nessdis reduced from its bulk value htoh
S, the effec-
tive slip length is given by b/H33527d/H20849h/H20862hS21/H20850. Previous
experiments with the SFA [29,30] and ・Ｐw measurements
through thin capillaries [31] indicate that the bulk liq-
uid viscosity is applicable down to separations below ten
molecular diameters. Thus, we believe that a reduced vis-cosity is not the reason for slip.
Signi ・…ant slip lengths of up to 20 nm were also found
by Craig et al. in aqueous sucrose solutions (viscosities
of0.01
0.08 Pa s) [20]. They measured hydrodynamic
forces between gold coated silica spheres and gold coatedmica. The gold surfaces were coated with a self-assembledmonolayer of alkanethiols leading to an advancing contactangle of 70
ﾂｱ. In their case, slip lengths increased with
increasing viscosity and shear rate. The aim of our study
was (i) to avoid problems of gold/thiol coating such as the
increased roughness, (ii) to use aqueous medium with itsnatural viscosity, and (iii) to use more hydrophilic surfaces.
Surface roughness could lead to an apparent slip length
because in contact the liquid can still ・Ｐw out of the gap
beside the asperities. To exclude this, we imaged the par-
ticles with a commercial AFM in contact mode (Fig. 2).The roughness of the particles was below 1 nm rms. Peak-to-valley distances of areas of 1mm
2were below 2 nm.
FIG. 2. AFM image of a glass particle recorded in contact
mode using oxide-sharpened tips. The right ・“ure was ・Ｂttened
and is shown at a height scale of 1 nm to show the roughness
in detail.Mica was atomically ・Ｂt. Thus, surface roughness can
probably not account for the slip lengths obtained. To ver-ify that our surfaces were hydrophilic, the receding contact
angleQ
rof our glass particles was determined by micro-
sphere tensiometry, where the interaction of the particlewith an air bubble in an aqueous medium is measured [32].We obtained zero contact angle. On mica also completewetting was observed.
Why did we detect slippage, while in previous experi-
ments no sign of slip was observed for water on smoothhydrophilic surfaces? One possible factor is the high shearrate we applied. For many liquids the viscosity dependson the shear rate [5,16,33], and experiments with partially
wetted surfaces [14,20] indicate that the slip length in-
creases with the shear rate. The maximal shear rate wascalculated according to Horn et al. [13] taking into ac-
count that the velocity of the particle decreases from n
0at
a large distance to zero for h!0. Typical maximal shear
rates were 6000 s21forn0/H3352720mm/H20862s and 9500 s21for
n0/H3352740mm/H20862s at a distance h/H335271nm.
Electrostatic force curves, recorded at low velocity at
pH 11 and in 2 mM salt, showed the characteristic ex-
ponentially decaying double-layer repulsion. When ・》ting
force curves with a constant charge model for the double-
layer force decay lengths of 6.9 nm were obtained. This
agrees with the calculated Debye length of lD/H335276.8nm.
The constant potential model deviated at h,15nm from
measured force curves.
FIG. 3 (color). Normalized electrostatic Fes(red, n0/H33527
0.2mm/H20862s,pH 11, 2 mM KOH) and electrokinetic force curve
Fek(black, n0/H3352740mm/H20862s,pH 11, 2 mM KOH). For compari-
son, also the hydrodynamic force Fhy(blue, n0/H3352740mm/H20862s,
pH 5, 200 mM KCl) taken with the same particle ( R/H3352710mm)
and cantilever is shown. In the range of the electric double
layer, the sum of the electrostatic and hydrodynamic force,
Fhy1Fes(green), is higher than the electrokinetic force curve.
Approaching and retracting forces curves are shown. The inset
shows the approaching force curves in more detail. Only each
10th data point is shown.
076103-3 076103-3
VOLUME 88, N UMBER 7 PHYSICAL REVIEW LETTERS 1 8F EBRUARY 2002
FIG. 4. Real velocity of the particle jdh/H20862dtjversus piezo
position for a typical hydrodynamic ( n0/H3352740mm/H20862s,pH5 ,
200 mM KCl, /H17006) and an electrokinetic force curve ( n0/H33527
40mm/H20862s,pH 11, 2 mM KCl, /H17033) recorded with the same
particle. Continuous lines show results of simulations.
Electrokinetic force curves were more repulsive than
electrostatic or hydrodynamic forces upon approach(Fig. 3). When retracting the particle, the electrostatic re-pulsion decreased the apparent hydrodynamic attractiveforce. The same results were obtained with NaCl, KCl,
KOH, NaOH, and KI. Hence, the effect did not depend on
the ion species. To simulate electrokinetic force curves,we took the hydrodynamic and double-layer forces intoaccount. Therefore, a term Ae
2h/H20862lDwas added on the left
side of Eq. (2). Here, Ais the amplitude of the electrostatic
double-layer repulsion. It was obtained by ・》ting electro-
static force curves for h.3nm with the constant charge
model. Good agreement between simulated and experi-mental force curves was achieved even for the retractingpart. We conclude that no special electrokinetic effect waspresent up to shear rates of typically 10
4s21.
Electrokinetic force curves were less repulsive than the
sum of the corresponding hydrodynamic and electrostaticforce curves in the approaching part (Fig. 3): F
ek,
Fhy1Fes. The reason is that when the particle ap-
proaches a charged surface and encounters an electrostatic
repulsion its velocity jdh/H20862dtjdecreases. The velocity in
the presence of electrostatic repulsion is lower than with-out a double layer (Fig. 4). This reduces the hydrodynamicforce and thus the total interaction.
We thank O. Vinogradova and G. Yakubov for helpful
discussions. We further acknowledge ・］ancial support
by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft grant Bu 701/14
(E. B.).
*Corresponding author.
Email address: butt@chemie.uni-siegen.de[1] J. N. Israelachvili, P. M. McGuiggan, and H. M. Homola,
Science 240,189 (1988).
[2] J. Van Alsten and S. Granick, Phys. Rev. Lett. 61,2570
(1988).
[3] J. Klein and E. Kumacheva, Science 269,816 (1995).
[4] M. Schoen, C. L. Rhykerd, D. J. Diestler, and J. H. Cush-
man, Science 245,1223 (1989).
[5] P. A. Thompson, G. S. Grest, and M. O. Robbins, Phys. Rev.
Lett. 68,3448 (1992).
[6] J. Gao, W. D. Luedtke, and U. Landman, Phys. Rev. Lett.
79,705 (1997).
[7] D. Y . C. Chan and R. G. Horn, J. Chem. Phys. 83,5311
(1985).
[8] W. J. Huisman, J. F. Peters, M. J. Zwanenburg, S. A.
de Vries, T. E. Derry, D. Abernathy, and J. F. van der Veen,
Nature (London) 390,379 (1997).
[9] A. K. Doerr, M. Tolan, T. Seydel, and W. Press, Physica
(Amsterdam) 248B ,263 (1998).
[10] C. J. Yu, A. G. Richter, J. Kmetko, A. Datta, and P. Dutta,
Europhys. Lett. 50,487 (2000).
[11] O. I. Vinogradova, Int. J. Miner. Process. 56,31 (1999).
[12] J. Baudry, E. Charlaix, A. Tonck, and D. Mazuyer,
Langmuir 17,5232 (2001).
[13] R. G. Horn, O. I. Vinogradova, M. E. Mackay, and N. Phan-
Thien, J. Chem. Phys. 112,6424 (2000).
[14] X. Zhu and S. Granick, Phys. Rev. Lett. 87,6105 (2001).
[15] M. Sun and C. Ebner, Phys. Rev. Lett. 69,3491 (1992).
[16] P. A. Thompson and S. M. Troian, Nature (London) 389,
360 (1997).
[17] M. J. Stevens, M. Mondello, G. S. Grest, S. T. Cui, H. D.
Cochran, and P. T. Cummings, J. Chem. Phys. 106,7303
(1997).
[18] P. G. de Gennes, C.R. Acad. Sci. B 288,219 (1979).
[19] R. Pit, H. Hervet, and L. L ﾃｩger, Phys. Rev. Lett. 85,980
(2000).
[20] V . S. J. Craig, C. Neto, and D. R. M. Williams, Phys. Rev.
Lett. 87,4504 (2001).
[21] P. Warszynski, Adv. Colloid Interface Sci. 84,47 (2000).
[22] S. G. Bike and D. C. Prieve, J. Colloid Interface Sci. 175,
422 (1995).
[23] S. Levine, J. R. Marriott, and K. Robinson, J. Chem. Soc.
Faraday Trans. 2 71,1 (1975).
[24] S. Ecke, R. Raiteri, E. Bonaccurso, C. Reiner, H. J.
Deiseroth, and H. J. Butt, Rev. Sci. Instrum. 72,4164
(2001).
[25] O. I. Vinogradova, H.-J. Butt, G. Yakubov, and F. Feuille-
bois, Rev. Sci. Instrum. 72,2330 (2000).
[26] J. E. Sader, J. Appl. Phys. 84,64 (1998).
[27] H. Brenner, Chem. Eng. Sci. 16,242 (1961).
[28] O. I. Vinogradova, Langmuir 11,2213 (1995).
[29] J. N. Israelachvili, J. Colloid Interface Sci. 110,263 (1986).
[30] U. Raviv, P. Laurat, and J. Klein, Nature (London) 413,51
(2001).
[31] N. V . Churaev, V . D. Sobolev, and A. N. Somov, J. Colloid
Interface Sci. 97,574 (1984).
[32] S. Ecke, M. Preuss, and H.-J. Butt, J. Adhes. Sci. Technol.
13,1181 (1999).
[33] H. W. Hu, G. A. Carson, and S. Granick, Phys. Rev. Lett.
66,2758 (1991).
076103-4 076103-4

